Jon Wayland

MSc Applied Math | MBA | AI Strategist

www.linkedin.com/in/jonwayland www.github.com/jonwayland https://jonwayland.com/

Applied Data Science Leader whose team innovates health solutions for under-65 Floridians using machine learning and advanced statistics. Passionate knowledge sharer who believes in results, furthering education, and ethical decision-making. Experienced professional in the fields of **healthcare** and **technology** as both a **thought leader** and **practitioner**.

Work Experience

Director, Data Science – Florida Blue (Blue Cross Blue Shield of FL)

Sr. Manager, Data Science (Jan. 2021 - Mar. 2023)

Sr. Data Scientist (Mar. 2020 - Jan. 2021)

Data Analytics Consultant (Mar. 2019 - Feb. 2020)

2019-Current | Jacksonville, FL

- Grew team of 1 to team of 8 full-time data scientists and engineers by proving the value of integrating data science into commercial markets initiatives
- Aligned ML strategy to enterprise needs by maintaining team's priorities with roadmaps, building trust in executives, and setting reliable expectations
- Pioneered new methodology for healthcare program evaluation resulting in a decreased difference in covariate means and variance for treatment and control matches by switching from propensity to distance matching
- Founded Member Funnel, an enterprise ID/Strat system and integrated DB
 - o 150+ clinical users; 150+ analytics users; 15+ ML models; 15+ data sources
 - Feeds all commercial, care management, rewards, <u>member website</u>,
 Provider Vista (external app.), and Care Connect (internal app.)
- Led end-to-end implementation on 20+ machine learning products
 - o Predicted end-of-life (9-15 months) for advanced care as an IC
 - XGBoost model with neural network-derived features (45% precision)
 - \$6.5M in annual savings w/ \$100k+ in direct admin. avoidance
 - o Incentivized quick turnarounds with modeling competitions
 - Successfully convinced for multiple in-house solutions over using vendors

Data Scientist – Availity

2017-2019 | Jacksonville, FL

- Increased provider service location accuracy by over 5% by embedding ML model into the <u>PDM product</u>
- Led cross-functional team resulting in segmenting Availity's user population
- Identified a subset of customers with high likelihood of attrition using registration DOW, slope of transaction volume, and login patterns

Business Analyst II – UPMC WorkPartners

Business Analyst I (Aug. 2014 – Feb. 2016)

2014-2017 | Pittsburgh, PA

- Predicted employees with longer return-to-work times after STD claims by combining randomForestSRC, k-means clustering, and logistic regression
- Led the repeatable integration of 9 commonly siloed data sources
- Contributed to acquisition of HCMS Group through validation of analytics

Various Part-Time Data Science Roles

2012-Current

- Freelancing Data Scientist <u>Upwork.com</u> | Virtual (2017-2021)
- Data Science Mentor <u>Springboard.com</u> | Virtual (2018-2020)
- Data Science Community TA <u>HarvardX</u> | Virtual (2019)
- Statistical Consultant <u>IUP Applied Research Lab</u> | Indiana, PA (2012 2014)

Technical Skills

Machine Learning

- o R, Python
- Defining outcomes
- o Data imbalance
- Cross validation
- Sampling techniques
- o Penalized regression
- Gradient boosting
- Prototyping
- Learning, understanding, and applying new algorithms quickly

> Data Wrangling

- SQL (SQL Server/DB2/Oracle/Hive)
- Web-scraping (XML/HTML)
- Regular expression (R/Python)

Leadership Skills

- o Bias for Action o Personable
- o Communication o Persuasive
- AssertiveSelf-Aware

Education

M.B.A. Entrepreneurship & Analytics

2019-2022

University of Illinois Urbana-Champaign

M.S. Applied Mathematics

2012-2014

Indiana University of Pennsylvania

B.S. Mathematics

2008-2012

Clarion University of Pennsylvania

Certifications

Professional Data Science Certificate

HarvardX on edX.org

Machine Learning Nanodegree

Udacity.com